Baburaj Kallarakkal

Senior Devops Engineer/Lead



248-229-3794



raj.anju@gmail.com



in https://www.linkedin.com

/in/baburajkallarakkal/

Senior Devops Engineer at Apple, responsible for the leadership of a portfolio of Devops(CI/CD) tooling infrastructure for Corporate Systems with an overall experience of 19+ years in **Information Technology**.

Extremely passionate, enabling the enablers by designing, scripting (Python) and implementing creative and scalable solutions on globally distributed technologies, made a real impact resulting in cost savings (96k+ annual) and brought quantitative efficiency by driving and bringing down production deployment run times from hours to under minutes.

Impulse to seek and explore emerging technologies, made a career progression from Java Programmer to Database Administrator and as a System Administrator (Linux) to SRE (Edge/Networking) with Oracle Cloud and finally landing into DevOps. Always inquisitive about Networking(Internet Routing/BGP/ASN), Cloud, Linux and Python.



Work History

2019-01 - Current

2015-10 - 2018-12

Senior Devops Engineer/Team Lead[AWS Certified]

Apple Inc., Austin, Texas

- Automated Elastic Search re-indexing using Python bringing substantial improvement in development cycles.
- Automated Life Cycle Management of Certificates using Python.
- Re-engineered systems to bring 72.2% improvement (reduced execution time from 8.2 hours to 1.2 hours)
- Engineered and automated systems for seamless migration of all Employee Systems VIPs from Legacy **DNS** to **GSLB**.
- Researched and build tools to bring multiple data sources to under one dashboard ES/Kibana using Python/JSON and REST APIs.
- Working closely with **Shield Team** to help find gaps and address them in (WAF) Web Application Firewall Rules.
- Deep dive to identify the gaps in vulnerability scans and engaging AIS to address the high critical CVE's.
- Actively running project to move legacy application to Kubernetes.
- Worked in Terraform and familiarity on AWS and GCP.
- Re-engineered systems to reduce execution times from 186 mins to under 10mins (Production release).

Senior SRE (Edge/DNS) [Redhat Certified Engineer]

Oracle Cloud Computing, Austin, TX

 Engineered and designed plan to migrate DNS zones to Dyn/Akamai from Legacy IPC systems backed by Ultra DNS.

- Part of rapid response team to triage edge cases involving DNS latencies(*wildcards), MTU, Jumbo frames, certificate expirations, Gateway/Routing errors on Overlay Networks, BGP flapping, Firewall issues and Database Overloads.
- Designed automations to lock down **Cloud Regions** before GA.
- Wrote several ansible playbooks to automate GRE,NTP, SIEM, PBRUN, LDAP on Cloud Regions.
- Participated in several fire-fights, triaging DNS/Nginx issues to stabilize several Oracle Public Cloud (LBaaS) regions.

2014-01 - 2015-09

System Administrator (Platform Engineering)

Oracle Cloud Computing, Austin, TX

- Worked in Platform Engineering Team responsible for the laaS code infrastructure for Oracle Cloud Compute (Chef).
- Responsible for writing Chef cookbooks for bootstrapping the instances across regions and providing support to the same.
- Developed **Python FAB**/screen **distributed** tooling for patching/automation of compute infrastructure.
- **SME for L2 escalations** for Cloud Services [Messaging, Developer and Data Cloud Services) ran in Oracle Public Cloud.
- Discovered critical security bug on Cloud Compute platform due to duplicate IP address on OVS/Exalogic and ZFS servers.
- Active contribution in troubleshooting and rolling out fixes using "ebtables" (MAC address layer) for Dom-U isolation with XEN (vif-*) scripts to prevent ARP Spoofing and NFS hacking.
- Triaging edge-cases across Cloud Regions involving complex networking issues using tcpdumps (MTU/Jumbo Frames)

2012-09 - 2013-12

Cloud SRE [Oracle Database Cloud]

Oracle Cloud Computing, Austin, TX

- Developed SOP's via automation using **Python**(FAB,Chef & Ansible) for L1 support teams.
- Automated patching framework using MCollective/Ruby for entire Java Cloud Service.
- Automated Dataguard Installations using bash/perl scripts for faster Exadata Database Cloud Service region setup.
- Part of team in building the entire region for Oracle Public Cloud.

2008-01 - 2012-06

Oracle Systems DBA [Oracle Certified Professional]

Ford Motor Credit, Dearborn, MI

- Resolution of numerous production issues involving sub second response times using AWR, ADDR and advanced monitoring.
- Systems DBA for Oracle with **24 x 7 support of 200+ databases** with financial critical data.
- Uncovered critical bugs (character set issues) due to UTF8/Unicode conversion as part of Asian/European Data Center Consolidation.
- Used Oracle's SCN technology to implement a Teradata Standby Database (open sourced article in the blog).

2002-09 - 2007-12

2000-05 - 2002-07

1999-11 - 2000-05

- Involved in performance tuning/debugging in all levels System, SQL, Linux, Database, and Network for application issues.workload.
- Developed multithreaded Java Program for performing Load Tests and obtain performance statistics for internal DBA Analysis.

Teradata DBA [Teradata Certified DBA]

Ford Motor Credit, Dearborn, MI

- Created a home grown Standby DB simulating Oracle's SCN technology
- Uncovered critical bugs (character set issues) due to UTF8/Unicode conversion as part of Asian/European Data Center Consolidation
- Developed as scalable solution to simulate load tests via Threads, Users,
 Dynamic SQL's via command line that goes against heterogeneous DB's

Datawarehouse Developer[Teradata Certified SQL]

Metiom, Merck Medco, The Limited, Kalki, New York, NY

 Worked on multi terabyte systems involving data migrations, data mining, SQL/PLSQL coding and several migration projects involving terabyte of warehouse data at Medco, The Limited and Intellisys.

Java Programmer [Sun Certified]

Kalki Communication Technologies, Bangalore, India

- Worked in B2B and PLC projects utilizing Java Networking, Servlets and Core Java Packages.
- Implemented Chat Server solutions with Java Sockets.



Skills

Databases - Elastic Search, Oracle, Teradata, MySQL

Programming - Java, Python, Bash, Terraform

Containers - Docker, Kubernetes

Monitoring - Splunk

Routing Layer - Apache, Nginx

CI/CD - Docker, GIT, Ansible

Cloud - Oracle Cloud, AWS (VPC/Networking Topology), EC2, S3

Networking - DNS,LBR,TCP/IP, BGP, Routing, SSL/TLS

Familiarity - GCP, AWS, Kafka Streaming, MongoDB, Kibana

Linux - Redhat, Oracle





Education

Master of Science: Management Information Systems
 Eastern Michigan University - Ypsilanti, MI

Bachelor of Technology

Government Engineering College - India

2006-01 - 2009-12

1995-12 - 1999-12



Certifications

2020-02

2018-07

2017-12

2007-08

2003-07

1999-10

- **AWS Certified Solutions Architect**
- Red Hat Certified Engineer
- Red Hat Certified System Administrator
- Oracle Certified Professional
- Teradata Certified Administrator
- Sun Certified Java Programmer



Accomplishments

- Innovated and implemented an automation solution resulting in substantial reduction of resources (144+ scripts deduced to 8) with a recurring savings of 120,000USD
- Discovered critical bug in Oracle Cloud Service involving duplicate IP addressing.
- Innovated and implemented system improvements to bring in 72% to up to 90% improvements in production deployments (Eg. Run times reduced from 186mins to under 10mins and 8.2hrs to 1.2hrs).
- Innovated and contributed an open source solution for Oracle Backups, rolled same internally to achieve 96,000+ storage costs.



Open Source Contributions

https://sourceforge.net/projects/oraclerman/ (Slide Deck -> http://padmavyuha.blogspot.com/2010/11/oraclerman-backup-solution-open-source.html)



Blog/Github

http://intercloudzone.com https://github.com/baburajk